<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Crostini on Explorations in software development</title>
    <link>https://www.tahoemph.blog/tags/crostini/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Crostini on Explorations in software development</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <managingEditor>tahoemph@gmail.com (Michael Hunter)</managingEditor>
    <webMaster>tahoemph@gmail.com (Michael Hunter)</webMaster>
    <copyright>(c) 2018 Michael Hunter</copyright>
    <atom:link href="https://www.tahoemph.blog/tags/crostini/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Crostini upgrade pain</title>
      <link>https://www.tahoemph.blog/post/crostini-upgrade-pain/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jul 2018 08:42:07 -0700</pubDate>
      <author>tahoemph@gmail.com (Michael Hunter)</author>
      <guid>https://www.tahoemph.blog/post/crostini-upgrade-pain/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Not all goes well when you are on the bleeding edge.  When upgrading from
&amp;ldquo;10798.0.0 (Official Build) dev-channel eve&amp;rdquo; to &amp;ldquo;Version 69.0.3473.0 (Official Build) dev (64-bit)&amp;rdquo;
I ended up encounting a problem.  Before upgrading I backedup all of my user files in the VM.  This
ended up saving me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After upgrade I was somewhat surprised that my VM seemed to be whole and viable.  But after less than
an hour the Chromebook froze and I needed to refresh-reboot it.  It came up but when I tried to start
the Terminal it spun and nothing happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ended up in crosh and ultimately removed the vm with &amp;lsquo;vmc destroy termina&amp;rsquo;.  This was after failure
attempting to start/stop the VM.  Then I could start a blank VM And restore my content losing only what
I had done in the interim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I gathered little data about what the problem was.  This was my first time on crosh.  I&amp;rsquo;ll have to
develop some muscle around manipulating VMs so that if I run into difficulties in the future I will
have a better chance of root causing and possibly saving the existing VM.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Crostini dev environment</title>
      <link>https://www.tahoemph.blog/post/crostini-dev-environment/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jul 2018 20:18:24 -0700</pubDate>
      <author>tahoemph@gmail.com (Michael Hunter)</author>
      <guid>https://www.tahoemph.blog/post/crostini-dev-environment/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have become less then enthused with the macOS envrionment due to its odd set of choices
and constant friction with open source tools.  My first thought was to
get a linux laptop thus removing the OSS friction.  I also tried an Ubuntu 18 install
on my MacBook but that had various issues and felt like a waste of the hardware.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like the idea of Chromebooks.
Security, long battery life, and a fair bit of stability are important to me for application
development tasks.  So I took several shots at using a Chromebook and finally
have found a development environment that works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First I tried this using termux following this
&lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.lessonslearned.org/building-a-more-secure-development-chromebook/&#34;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt;
using a Samsung Chromebook Plus.  This is an ARM based machine which a really nice IPS
screen.  Somewhere between the processor maybe not having enough oomph and setting
up the termux based environment this failed.  It felt clunky and not something that
would be easy to maintain and update.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About the time I gave up on termux Google
&lt;a href=&#34;https://liliputing.com/2018/04/googles-crostini-lets-you-run-gnu-linux-apps-on-chromebooks-without-enabling-developer-mode.html&#34;&gt;announced&lt;/a&gt;
a VM based dev solution on Chromebooks called Crostini.  Initially it was very limited but it has grown
some reasonable capabilities.  Currently I am using &lt;del&gt;&amp;ldquo;10798.0.0 (Official Build) dev-channel eve&amp;rdquo;&lt;/del&gt;&amp;ldquo;Version 69.0.3473.0 (Official Build) dev (64-bit)&amp;rdquo;.  With this upgrade tmux now works.  Yea!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Configuration information is available
&lt;a href=&#34;https://chromium.googlesource.com/chromiumos/docs/+/master/containers_and_vms.md&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Future articles will go into issues I encounter and how to resolve them.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>